Exercise sheet number 11, task number one.
To solve this task, we need to use the method
from the lecture.
This is the method from the lecture written
in English.
And these are the three steps, creating the
complementary states so that the sum of the
tokens in the state and its complementary
state always results in the desired capacity.
The second step is if a transition t altogether
takes away tokens from a state s in such a
way, then we add an edge from t to s-bar with
the weight minus n.
The third step is, if a transition altogether
adds tokens to a state s in such a way, then
insert an edge from s-bar to this transition
with the weight n.
Let's apply this method to the Petri net that
we have.
I'm going to write the capacities here.
And let's do the first step.
So, for s1, let's make a complimentary state
s1-bar.
And how many tokens are we going to put inside
it?
As I said before, s1 has a capacity of two
and it already has two tokens.
This means we don't add any tokens here.
The same goes for s2, it has a capacity
of two, and it already has two tokens.
This means for s2-bar, we don't add any tokens.
Let's make a complimentary state for s3, s3-bar.
And because the capacity of s3 is one and
it doesn't have any tokens, this means we
add one token here.
Now, s4-bar, the capacity of s4 is three,
and s4 doesn't have any tokens.
This means we add three tokens to s4-bar.
Now, step two.
T1 takes one token from s1.
This means we do an edge from t1 to s1-bar
like this.
T2 takes a token from s2, we do an edge from
t2 to the complement of s2 like this.
T3 takes a token from s3.
So, we do an edge from t3 to the complement
of s3 like this.
T4 takes a token from s4, we do an edge from
t4 to the complement of s4 like this.
T5 takes a token from s4.
So, we do an edge from t5 to the complement
of s4 like this.
Now step three.
T1 gives a token to s3.
This means it should take a token from the
complement of s3 like this.
T2 gives a token to s3.
This means it should take a token from the
complement of s3.
T3 gives a token to s4.
This means it should take a token from the
complement of s4.
T4 gives a token to s1.
This means it should take a token from the
complement of s1.
T5 gives a token to s2.
This means it should take a token from the
complement of s2.
And we are done.
So now we can remove the capacities.
The capacities here we don't need them anymore
because this Petri net is now equivalent to
the original Petri net that we had which have
capacities.